Guide to the Department of Agricultural Economics Research Project Records 1911-1963
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Department of Agricultural Economics Research Project Records
1911-1963
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
MSU.73039
22 linear feet
The Department of Agricultural Economics Research Project Records consist of files that document the activities of various personnel in surveying and interpreting agricultural development in Montana. The subjects of the various projects include rural housing, financing, dairy operations, rural electrification, meat trade, irrigation, and taxation.
Folder-os 1
This collection is open for research.
The records of the Department of Agricultural Economics were transferred to the University Archives in 1973.
Series 1 Economic Study of Hunting and Fishing in Montana 1960-1961
Series 2 Marketing Cooperatives Serving Livestock Industry, 1957-1961
Series 3 Barley Prices, 1960-1962
Series 4 Livestock Shrinkage, 1960-1963
Series 5 Cooperative Grain Elevator Study, 1957-1958
Series 6 Grain Storage and Handling Study, 1961-1963
Series 7 Baker, Electric Power - Western Montana Stock Ranches, 1940-1952
Series 8 Factors Influencing Availability of Rural Housing Credit in Montana, 1963
Series 9 Survey of Home Mortgage Lending, 1963
Series 10 Factors Related to Consumer Meat Buying Decisions,1962-1963
Series 11 Rural Problem Areas Survey, 1934
Series 12 Field Schedules, Bulletin 453
Series 13 Beet Labor Project, 1939
Series 14 Farm and Ranch Schedules 1950s or 60s
Series 15 Merchant and Dealer Schedules 1950s or 60s
Series 16 Shonkin Electric Line Study
Series 17 Schedules for Soil Conserving Practices
Series 18 Various Research Reports and Data
Series 19 Cooperative Elevator Study, 1939
Series 20 Collective Tenure, 1942
Series 21 Farm Security Administration Records--Summary
Series 22 Flathead Cream Marketings, 1953-1954
Series 23 Deadman Basin Project (Irrigation) and others
Series 24 Blackfeet Ranching Study
Series 25 Craig Ranch Study, 1942
Series 26 Technical Committee -- Tenure
Series 27 Sinclair Farm Record Analysis, 1923-1939
Series 28 Dairy Study, 1957
Series 29 Cooperative Farm Management Study--Agricultural Economics Dept. and BAE
Series 30 Beaverhead County Survey, 1919
Series 31 Wibaux County Survey, 1919-1920
Series 32 Successful Farms, 1921
Series 33 State Farmer Loans
Series 34 Farm Real Estate Mortgage and Foreclosure Study, 1911-1938
Series 35 Thesis Material for M.E. Quenemon, 1952
Series 36 Public Welfare reports for Ravalli County, 1930s
Series 37 Tax Delinquency Information, 1930s
Series 38 Breeding Improvement Work, 1928-1935
Series 39 Farm Account Project, 1925-1929
Series 40 Saunderson Projects, 1923-1938
Series 41 Land Pricing Study, 1957
Series 42 Farm Labor, 1942
Series 43 Farm Tax Data, 1920s-1933
Series 44 Foreclosure Data, 1900-1936
The roots of the Agricultural Economics Department at Montana State University reach back to the Farm Management program in 1913. Classes in the beginning stages were instructed by E. L. Currier, whose main priority was teaching basic accounting principles to working farmers after these practices were found to be deficient. With the passage of the Purnell Act in 1925, the college was granted much needed funds to begin a curriculum focusing on the agricultural economics field. Director Linfield dismantled the Farm Management Department and put this new field under the wing of the Experiment Station. Although M. L. Wilson was named its first head, actual leadership came from former M. S. C. president James Hamilton while Wilson finished up his graduate work at the University of Wisconsin. Once Mr. Wilson took charge of the department in 1925, he was not an instructor but a researcher with the Experiment Station. His projects in collaboration with E. A. Starch deal with transforming dry farming and making agriculture more profitable. Aside from his work on the "Fairway Farms project," Wilson also did a great deal of research to publish Dry Farming in the North Central Montana Triangle, Extension Service Bulletin 66 (Bozeman, Montana State College: June 1923). The study centered on an area roughly encompassed by Havre, Great Falls, and Cut Bank, Montana, and discussed the reasons for the success and failure of the region's farmers. Many of the Agricultural Economics faculty and staff assisted in gathering the data used for this report, and when Wilson left the University to take a post within the Roosevelt administration and E. A. Starch took over as Head of the Department in 1933, research projects on all aspects of Montana agriculture continued, not necessarily restricted to the "triangle" area.
The Agricultural Economics Department Research Project Records are an extensive set of files that document the activities of various personnel in surveying and interpreting agricultural development in Montana. While some of the material may have been used by Wilson in preparing his 1923 publication, specifically those in Series 32, "Successful Farms," most of these research projects took place afterwards. The subjects of the various projects include rural housing, financing, dairy operations, rural electrification, meat trade, irrigation, and taxation. Investigators include Richard J. McConnen, Pius Weisgerber, Clive Harston, Laurence O. Baker, Jack R. Davidson, Roy E. Huffman, D.C. Myrick, Glenn H. Craig, Charles W. Loomer, M.E. Quenemoen, M.H. Saunderson Paul Pilati, W. Rehberg, and H. Walton. The records have been divided into 43 series titled with the project name.
Agriculture-Montana-Economic aspects; Dairying-Montana; Dry farming-Montana; Housing, Rural-Montana; Irrigation-Montana; Meat industry and trade-Montana; Rural electrification-Montana; Taxation-Montana; Walton, H
Agriculture; Colleges and Universities; Montana; Bozeman
- Economic Study of Hunting and Fishing in Montana, 1960-1961; 1
  Richard J. McConnen served as the principal investigator for this study. This series consists of memoranda, notes, tables of figures, handwritten description of the study, survey forms, and statistical figures. The Economic Survey consists of a series of mimeographed tables with figures. No written summary of this study is present.
  - R.J. McConnen, Economic Study (Box 1, Folder 1-21)
- Marketing Cooperatives Serving Livestock Industry, 1957-1961; 2
  Pius Weisberger served as the principal investigator for this study. This contains no final report. Included are a research project statement, meeting memo, proposal on a regional project, a talk by Ira M. Stevens, and a paper on the marketing of lambs.
  - Potentialities of Cooperatives In Assisting Montana Farms to Market Excess Grains Through Livestock (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Barley Prices, 1960-1962; 3
  This series provides the name of no principal investigator nor does it contain a summary or final report. It includes handwritten notes, Federal Register reprints, a graph, barley shipments via rail for Montana, other railroad freight for 1960-61, a barley production/animal unit chart, and a price per bushel/bushels per animal chart.
  - Barley Prices, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Livestock Shrinkage, 1960-1963; 4
  Clive Harston of Montana State College's Department of Agricultural Economics served as the principal investigator. Series 4 concerns loss of weight in livestock during shipment and its effects on market price received by western stock raisers. It contains pamphlets on the general topic of shrinkage, lambs, announcements, requests for copies and draft reviews, draft of circular, handwritten notes, other related papers and clippings, and field notes of interviews. The first and second of the planned series of three circulars (#s 220-222), "Cattle Shrinkage Depends on How You Market," "Cattle Shrinkage: Depends on Where, When and What You Market," are present in mimeographed form.
  - Livestock Shrinkage, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 24-29)
- Cooperative Grain Elevator Study, 1957-1958; 5
  Clive R. Harston of Montana State College's Department of Agricultural Economics served as the principal investigator for this study. This series includes letters of suggestion that a study be done, letters pleading lack of funding for such a project, booklets/pamphlets on cooperative grain marketing and elevators, a final report form, an annual progress report form, and a research project statement. There is no final, full report in this series.
  - Cooperative Grain Elevator Study, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
- Grain Storage and Handling Study, 1961-1963; 6
  The principal investigator was Clive R. Harston of Montana State College's Department of Agricultural Economics. Items include a research project statement, notes, correspondence, and a study contract draft. There is no final report in this series.
  - Grain Storage and Handling Study, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Electric Power - Western Montana Stock Ranches, 1940-1952; 7
  The name of a Dr. Baker appears on one of the items. This may be Laurence O. Baker who was an assistant professor of Agronomy at this time. This series includes work tables, notes, charts, and survey forms. There is no final report in this series.
  - Electric Power on Stock Ranches, Work Tables (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Baker, Electric Power Study (Box 1, Folder 34-42)
  - Electric Power Use Records and User Permits (Box 1, Folder 43-45)
  - Baker, Electric Power Study (Box 1, Folder 46-54)
  - Electric Power Consumption Records and Annual Cost for Each Ranch in Electric Power Consumption Study (Box 1, Folder 55-59)
  - Baker, Electric Power Study (Box 1, Folder 60-70)
  - Baker, Electric Power Study (Box 2, Folder 1-29)
- Factors Influencing Availability of Rural Housing Credit in Montana, 1963; 8
  This series consists of questionnaires, theses, and a final report, which appears as Montana Agricultural Experiment Station Bulletin 586. Principal investigators included Robert L. Sargent, graduate research assistant at MSC, Jack R. Davidson, Associate Professor, Department of Agricultural Economics and Rural Sociology, Montana Agricultural Experiment Station, Bozeman, and Lawrence A. Jones, agricultural economist, Economic Research, U.S.D.A. The purpose of this study was "to determine whether or not credit is as readily available for home building, remodeling or purchasing in rural areas as in the urban areas of Montana." Bulletin 586 is in Box 3, Folder 4. A mimeo of Robert L. Sargent's thesis, "Availability of Rural Housing Credit in Montana," has been removed from this collection since the thesis is available in MSU library. The series also includes a mimeo of "Availability of Rural Housing Credit in Montana," with some variation from the bulletin, in Box 3, Folders 5-8.
  - Factors Influencing Availability of Rural Housing Credit in Montana, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 30-70)
  - Factors Influencing Availability of Rural Housing Credit in Montana, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 1-10)
- Survey of Home Mortgage Lending, 1963; 9
  Principal investigators are not listed. This series includes survey forms presented to commercial bank real estate brokers, attorneys, and similar individuals, mortgage companies, agents, savings and loan associations in Montana, correspondence, and questionnaires.
  - Survey of Home Mortgage Lending, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 11-24)
- Factors Related to Consumer Meat Buying Decisions, 1962-1963; 10
  This series consists of survey forms labeled as "personal interview." Montana areas surveyed included, Butte, Billings, Dillon, Glendive, Great Falls, Havre, Kalispell, Shelby, and Sidney. Information on these forms includes the sex of the interviewee, meats purchased, shopping frequency, influences and habits, meat consumption during week, occupation, age, education, home when growing up, years in Montana, and income.
  - Factors Related to Consumer Meat Buying Decisions, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 25-80)
  - Factors Related to Consumer Meat Buying Decisions, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 1-96)
  - Factors Related to Consumer Meat Buying Decisions, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 1-90)
  - Factors Related to Consumer Meat Buying Decisions, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 1-32)
- Rural Problem Areas Survey, 1934; 11
  This series includes surveys of Phillips, Prairie, and Yellowstone Counties. It comprises information on poor farms, delinquent children, housing, mortgages, grazing capacity, families on relief survey forms, aid applications, maps, county agent annual reports, occupations, survey report forms, and ownership. A survey report for Phillips County is in Folders 40-44 and consists of charts, graphs, and tables. The Report on Survey of Prairie County is in Folders 61-66. A survey report for Yellowstone County is in Folders 74-75 with some tables missing.
  - Rural Problem Areas Survey, Phillips, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 33-56)
  - Rural Problem Areas Survey, Prairie, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 57-75)
- Field Schedules, Bulletin 453, 1948; 12
  This includes schedules for "Farm Organization and Production Requirements in Selected Irrigated Areas," and is dated October 1948. Roy E. Huffman and D.C. Myrick served as principal investigators. Schedules include information on the area of owned and rented cropland, grazing, livestock, crop types, irrigation, crop rotation, fertilizer and manuring, farm labor, inter-farm cooperation, mechanical and other innovations, machinery and equipment, and farm expenses and receipts.
  - Field Schedules, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 76-97)
  - Field Schedules, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 1-27)
- Beet Labor Project, 1939; 13
  Includes family schedules providing names of owners, farm location, numbers in family and household, nationality, beet acreage, division of earning, and notations. Solo Worker Schedules include owner or tenant name, numbers of workers, wage agreement, resident and migrant workers with nationalities, contracted acres, and notations.
  - Beet Labor Project, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 28-41)
- Farm & Ranch Schedules, circa 1950s or 1960s; 14
  Farm and ranch schedules include name, address, ages farm experience, supply center location and distance from farm, type of farming, how started in farming, land used in crop production, real estate indebtedness, production credit, machinery and improvement financing, attitudes, farm supply expenditures, family living expense, major farm improvements, livestock enterprises, and machinery and equipment.
  - Farm & Ranch Schedules (Box 7, Folder 42-44)
  - Farm & Ranch Schedules (Box 8, Folder 1-6)
- Merchant & Dealer Schedules, circa 1950s or 1960s; 15
  Merchant and Dealer Schedules provide information on location, type of merchandise, sales to farmers, farmer credit sales, interest charges and terms of repayment, credit extended on open account, basis for credit arrangements, credit terms on open account purchases, loss on open account credit, opinions on credit use, prefer cash or credit terms, sales vs. credit, and presence of credit department.
  - Merchant & Dealer Schedules (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Shonkin Electric Line Study, 16
  This study includes a handwritten "Report on Economic Study of the Shonkin Extension of the Sun River Electric Coop" by L. Thompson (pages missing); various tables constructed from collected data; Summary Sheet—Farm Records which cover crop and land use, feed use, land, building, livestock, equipment, and credits and debts inventories, electric equipment, miscellaneous factors, and notes.
  - Shonkin Electric Line Study (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
- Schedules for Soil Conserving Practices, 17
  These schedules include data about land location, name and address of owner, erosion, strip cropping, crop residues, use of permanent vegetative cover, renovating land in permanent cover, water facilities, diversion ditches for flood irrigation, windbreaks, contour furrows on pasture land, and effect on farm organization and management.
  - Schedules for Soil Conserving Practices — Culbertson (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Schedules for Soil Conserving Practices — Dutton (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Various Research Reports and Data, 18
  Includes information on numbers and acreages of wheat farms, combination farms, and stock ranches, seeded wheat acres, wheat yields, feed crops, animal units, and area summaries; progress in studies; agricultural policy material concerning requisitions, emergency war agencies, responsibilities of agencies, Northern Plains Regional Study, Northwest Regional Council, new research projects, Chronology of American Agriculture (1790-1940), and commodity reports; old frequencies; worksheets; resource productivity data; computation sheets; miscellaneous; dairy sales; crop types in counties; industrial incomes; income material; labor earnings; livestock industry; livestock income shares; experiment station financial report; livestock contributions; agricultural production; Canadian agriculture; wheat, hay, sugar beets, flax, potatoes, rye, barley, oats, corn horses, mules, and cattle data; Northern Plains tenure; Montana plains type of farming; flax and tariff; range and livestock; ranch management and organization, farm records and accounts; forms for feeding records, farm business records, farm tractor records, farm inventory.
  - Old Frequencies Area III (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Inventories of Progress (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Agricultural Policy Material (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Old Frequencies Now Superseded, Area V (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Work Sheets Area III (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Resource Productivity on Dryland Crop Farms — Sampling Data (Box 8, Folder 17-18)
  - Computation Sheets for Area III (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Materials (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Dairy Sales Distribution and Seasonal Variation — Flathead (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - C.R. 9 Carter (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - C.R. 9 Rosebud (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Incomes Produced by Industries (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Income Material (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Economic Division Memos (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Alberta Data (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Marketing Act, 1934-1935 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Labor Earnings (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript: Income Study (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript: Livestock Income Shares (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript: Livestock Industry (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Financial Report: Montana State College, Montana Experiment Station, 1932-1933 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Livestock Contributions (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Assessments (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Agricultural Income and Production (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Thesis, Alberta Drought Area (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Canadian Agriculture (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - County and District Data (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Northern Plains Tenure Manuscript and Letters (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Northern Plains Tenure Manuscript (Final Draft) and Letters (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Montana Great Plains Regional Map: Type of Farming (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Flax and Tariff Changes, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Northern Plains Tenure Committee Correspondence (Tootell) (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Livestock and Range (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Proposal for an Economic Study of Ranch Management and Organization in Montana (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Record Forms (Box 9, Folder 21)
- Cooperative Elevator Study, 1939, 19
  Glenn H. Craig was the principal investigator for this study which covers areas in Canada and Montana. Numbers in parentheses represent the schedule numbers assigned to the original folders in this study. Data includes name and location of the elevator, corporate and cooperative features, management, membership, credit analysis, side lines and services, general information, assets, liabilities, grain, surplus analysis, shipping record, selected statistics, balance sheets, operating statements, comparative statistics, income, and sales. Box 10, Folder 18 contains "Preliminary Analysis of Farmer's [sic] Elevator Operations, 1937-1938."
  - Dutton Farmers' Elevator Company (#81) (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Farmers' Grain Exchange, Havre (#82) (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Powers Farmers' Elevator Co. (#83) (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Equity Cooperative Association, Brady (#84) (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Equity Cooperative Association, Conrad, (#85) (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Farmers' Cooperative Elevator Co., Denton (#86) (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Farmers' Elevator and Trading Co., Fort Benton (#87) (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Square Butte Elevator Co., Square Butte (#88) (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Farmers' Union Elevator Co., Joplin (#89) (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Farmers Coop Co., Carter (#90) (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Dutton Coop Association (#91) (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Union Elevator Co., Galata (#93) (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Farmers' Union Elevator Co., Inverness (#94) (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Farmers' Union Elevator Co., Ledger (#95) (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Farmers' Union Elevator Co., Rudyard (#96) (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - Farmers' Union Elevator Co., Valier (#97) (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - Equity Supply Co., Kalispell (#98) (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - Equity Coop Association, Geraldine (#99) (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - Hingham Farmers' Elevator Co. (#100) (Box 9, Folder 40)
  - Equity Coop Association, Ulm (#101) (Box 9, Folder 41)
  - Equity Cooperative Association of Farmington (#102) (Box 9, Folder 42)
  - Farmers' Union Elevator Co., Chinook (#103) (Box 9, Folder 43)
  - Equity Cooperative Association, Inc., Harlem (#104) (Box 9, Folder 44)
  - Equity Coop Assoc., Malta (#105) (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Farmers' Union Elevator Company, Glasgow (#106) (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Nashua Farmers' Union Cooperative Elevator Company (#107) (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Equity Cooperative Association, Wolf Point (#108) (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Farmers' Elevator Company, Culbertson (#109) (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Farmers' Union Grain Terminal Association, McCabe (#110) (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Farmers' Elevator Company, Froid (#111) (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Farmers' Elevator Company, Homestead (#112) (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Farmers' Elevator Company, Reserve (#113) (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Farmers' Grain and Shipping Company, Antelope (#114) (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Farmers' Grain and Trading Company, Westby (#115) (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Equity Cooperative Association, Raymond (#116) (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Farmers' Elevator Company, Outlook (#117) (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Farmers' Cooperative Grain and Mercantile Company, Flaxville (#118) (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Farmers' Elevator Company, Scobey (#119) (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Four Buttes Farmers' Elevator Company (#120) (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Farmers' Union Elevator Company, Peerless (#121) (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Farmers' Union Elevator Company, Richland (#122) (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Farmers' Union Elevator Company, Opheim (#123) (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Farmers' Mercantile Elevator Company, Sidney (#124) (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Farmers' Union Elevator Company, Lambert (#125) (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Farmers' Union Elevator Company, Richey (#126) (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Farmers' Union Elevator Company, Circle (#127) (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Farmers' Union Cooperative Elevator, Savage (#128) (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Wibaux Cooperative Elevator Company (#129) (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Carlyle Farmers' Elevator Company (#130) (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Farmers' Cooperative Association, Plevna (#131) (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Equity Cooperative Association, Vananda (#132) (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Molt Farmers' Elevator Company (#133) (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Columbus Farmers' Elevator Company (#134) (Box 10, Folder 30)
- Collective Tenure, 1942; 20
  Includes original manuscript for "Collective Tenure in Montana" by Glenn H. Craig and Charles W. Loomer, the principal investigators for this study.
  - Collective Tenure, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 31-33)
- Farm Security Administration Records—Summary, 21
  Partial records summary provides some data for 1940 farm size, expenses, income, and resources.
  - FSA Records—Summary, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 34)
- Flathead Cream Marketing, 1953-1954; 22